JOE: If change is inevitable then
individuals with autism can be helped
and guided through the process by
using strategies to prepare and
support them through those changes.
BETH: If a change is due to happen
at school, parents and carers
can be proactive in finding out
about what the changes will be.
If there is to be a new teacher
or new classrooms, by finding
out what is involved in advance,
parents and carers can work out any
impact it might have on a child.
JOE: The day of the change can be marked
on a calendar and the child can be
encouraged to count down to that day.
Describing the change clearly
gives the child time to process the
information along with visual supports.
Visual supports like social stories
and photos can be used to show the
outcome of activities such as going
on holiday and all that goes with it.
BETH: Showing a photo of a plane and a
hotel may make an individual nervous to go
on a plane or concerned about the hotel.
But if the whole process is
documented from start to finish
and shown visually including lots
of photos of the destination, this
will help them to understand more.
The whole process can then be reversed
to show the journey back and show that
they are going to be returning home
to somewhere and something familiar.
Visual timetables can also help to
make the processes more straightforward
and prepare them for the trip.
JOE: Visual supports such as photos
can help in preparing individuals with
autism for a new place for a visit
such as a stately home, a new person
in their life, like a support worker
or a new activity such as swimming.
Making a book of photos, or a collection
of images on their device, can
give them an opportunity to look at
something before and during the change.
BETH: If the change is because of a move
to a new school or care service, staff
that the individual will interact with,
should be a key part of the preparations.
They could be introduced to them
in familiar surroundings and
then be introduced to the new
environment by photos and a visit.
JOE: Problems with sequencing can often
cause problems with behaviour when
transitioning between activities, for
example becoming anxious at school or
college over unstructured break times.
Visual timetables either digital
or physical can help to alleviate
stress and timer alerts can inform
when things are over or due to start
making a timeframe more structured.
BETH: Whatever the change, if the
individual can be prepared in some
way for what is about to happen, then
they have the time to process the
information and deal with it more
appropriately from an informed position.